ウッ！ウッ！ウグッ！ウグッ‼
なんば　ひびと
(南波日々人)ウッ！フッ！
おれ
俺 リハビリなんていらね～のに｡
(バディ)バカ言うなヒビト！➡
I don't need any rehab...
Don't be stupid, Hibito!
You were in an accident.
じこ
あんな事故のあとだぜ｡オレの
だま
考えたメニューを黙ってやれって｡
Shut up, and follow the regimen I gave you!
Then, let me ask you this, Buddy...
じゃあ 訊くけどさ バディ
きた
これはどこを鍛えてんだよ！
Which body part am I working on?
しり
え～っと これはなぁ…尻だ｡
足だろ‼
Uh, this particular exercise is for...
your butt.
Not my legs?!
If you already know, don't stop.
わかってんなら続けろよ！
チェッ…｡
せんがいかつどう
《船外活動すんのが 俺には
一番のﾘﾊﾋﾞﾘだと思うけどな｡➡
Personally, I think the best rehab would be some extravehicular activity.
月に来て２ヶ月｡あっという間に
過ぎちまったなぁ》
It's been two months since we landed on the moon.
The time's flown by...
[TV]消えた？
かんせいかん
(管制官)そうだ➡
Gone?
Yes, we suddenly lost our signal from the unmanned probe Gibson.
たんさ
つうしん
無人探査機ギブソンとの通信が
とだ
急に途絶えた｡
[TV](管制官)
日々人が光るものを見たと
いってた辺りでプッツリだ｡
It happened near the area where you described seeing a flash.
よう
なるほど｡要するに
俺とダミアンで➡
Understood.
In that case,
Damian and I just need to find Gibson and repair it?
ギブソンを見つけ出して
しゅうり
修理すれば いいわけね｡
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)そうだ ヒビト｡
足元のボックスに➡
Oh right, Hibito...
There should be a manual for Gibson in the box by your feet.
てじゅんしょ
ギブソンの手順書があるはずだ｡
修理関連のページ 読んどいて｡
りょうかい
あ 了解｡
Can you read the part on repairs?
Sure, roger that.
あれ 開かねえ｡うっ…｡
Huh? It won't open.
Turn the lever left.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)レバーを左に回すんだよ｡
うう…レバーって？どっちの？
Which lever?
Hmm? There should be only one.
あれ？本当だ ２つある｡
Huh? You're right.
There are two.
はっ…ああ～っ‼
SPACE BROTHERS
You've always been in my heart
But you don't say a thing or even smile
We've always been together
We're ignorant, but we believe
All the time I spent with you
Felt like a dream
We connected the stars and drew pictures
To our hearts' content
Let our hearts, shivering in excitement,
Use the sky as a canvas
And merge to form an everlasting image
#53 Stand on the Moon Together Alive
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅ヒビトは自分が死んだら
どうなると思う？⦆
Hibito, what do you think happens after you die?
⦅ん？さあ…わかんないけど⦆
I'm not sure...
⦅生まれてない時と
同じだと思う⦆
Wouldn't it be like before I was born?
てんごく
じごく
⦅じゃあ 天国とか地獄は？⦆
Then what about heaven and hell?
I don't believe in either one.
⦅俺はないと思うな どっちも⦆
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅なぜ？⦆
Why not?
Because you can only see heaven and hell
⦅だって 天国も地獄もどっちも…
生きてる時に見るもんだ⦆
when you're alive.
ダミアン…どこ行った？
Damian...
Where are you?
こちらヒューストン！
ダミアン ヒビト 応答してくれ！
This is Houston.
Damian, Hibito, come in.
じょうきょう
ほうこく
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)状況を 報告しろ｡
ﾈｯﾄﾜｰｸ！どうなってる？
Give me a status update.
NETWORK, what's happening?
(管制官)ダミアンとヒビトの
とだ
通信が途絶えました｡
We've lost contact with Damian and Hibito.
Last transmission was near Mons Brandenburger.
ブランブルック山付近です｡
《こ…この わだちは…
バギーの！》
Th-These tracks...
They're from the buggy!
《いや バギーは真っすぐ
落ちて行ったはず》
No,
the buggy fell down here.
Why would there be tracks?
《なんで横に…》
ギブソン こんな所に
いやがったか｡
Gibson...
So this is where you were.
Man, you're the reason we're stuck down here.
まったく…お前のおかげで
はめ
こんな羽目に｡
But I guess a machine
きかい
お前みたいな機械でも ちょっとは
マシにさせてくれるもんだな｡
is still better than nothing.
こどく
お前にあうまでの孤独感は
けっこう
結構ヤバかったよ｡
I was feeling pretty alone before I ran into you.
しょうめいだん
ばくはつ
《ダミアン‼…無事だったか！》
Damian... You're okay?
ちょうせつ
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ 体温調節システムが
こしょう
故障したらしい｡➡
My temperature regulation system is busted.
じゅんかん
水の循環が
悪くなってるようで…➡
I'm not getting enough water...
My body is freezing.
こお
体が凍りそうに寒い｡➡
ブライアンとの話を
思い出してたんだ｡➡
I was remembering what Brian told us...
わかるだろ ヒビト？
I know you understand, Hibito.
If two astronauts conducting an EVA have an accident,
⦅２人での船外活動中
何らかの事故により➡
and one astronaut cannot be saved,
仲間の命が助からないと
はんだん
判断できる時➡
せいかん
これを切り捨て 自分の生還を
第一に考えること⦆
you must abandon that astronaut, to prioritize your own survival.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
俺を置いて行ってくれ｡
Leave me behind.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
俺はさ ダミアン…あんたの命を
助けられると判断してるよ｡➡
Guess what, Damian?
I'm saying that I can save your life.
かげ
４時間もこのマイナス170度の影に
いたら ダミアンの命が危ない｡➡
After four hours in the -170 °C dark,
your life will be in danger.
ちょっと ここで待ってろよ
ダミアン｡
Wait here for a moment, Damian.
(ガガーン ガラガラ)
(ドスン ゴゴッ…)
《ヒ…ヒビト！》
H-Hibito...
H-Hey!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)お おい…ヒビト！
Hibito...
《ヒビト…》
Hibito!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
しょうげき
うう…なんだ 今の衝撃｡
What was that shock wave?
クソッ！
Crap!
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
なんだよ ダミアン｡
What's wrong, Damian?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
さんそ
酸素のメインタンクが…➡
Your main oxygen tank
はそん
破損してる‼
has been punctured!
ざんりょう
《メインタンク酸素残量ゼロ…｡➡
My main tank's empty.
予備タンク酸素残量…８０分》
My backup tank has...
eighty minutes!
Eighty minutes...
《８０分…》
Do I have enough time?
《間に合うのか!?➡
How much longer will it take Freddy and the rest to arrive?
フレディ達が来るのは
今から え～っと…➡
Damn, stay calm!
くそっ 落ち着け》
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
俺は…助からないかもしれない…｡
This might be the end for me.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
やっぱり俺を置いていけヒビト｡➡
You should leave me here, Hibito.
お前１人なら…なんとか上まで…｡
If you're alone, you can make it up there.
《ダミアン…➡
Damian...
As a kid, I dreamed of going to the moon...
すなお
俺がガキの頃 素直に
月へ行きたいって思えたのは➡
きっと アポロの飛行士たちが
みんな無事に➡
because the Apollo astronauts
all returned alive!
ちゃんと帰ってきたからだ！》
《帰るぞ！》
We're going to make it home!
照明弾が光った位置から
２人が移動していなければ➡
If they haven't moved from the area where the flare was launched,
Freddy and Buddy will be able to
haul them up, once they arrive.
フレディたちが到着しだい すぐに
ウインチで引き上げられる｡➡
大丈夫！２人は
必ず助かるよ エディ｡
Don't worry.
They'll be fine, Eddie.
(飛行士)エディ｡
Eddie...
いの
(エディ)２人の無事を祈ろう｡
Let us pray for their safe return.
俺たちに出来るのはそれくらいだ｡
That's all that we can do.
《俺達のバギーが この谷を
まっすぐ落ちたのに対して➡
Our buggy dropped straight to the bottom of the ravine,
しゃめん
ギブソンは斜面を横方向に
ゆっくり降りて来ている｡➡
but Gibson rolled down at an angle.
けいしゃ
ゆる
こいつは傾斜の緩いコースを
知ってるはずだ｡➡
This boy knows which route won't be too steep.
来た道をたどって帰らせる｡
たく
ギブソンに託そう｡➡
We can follow his tracks back.
It's all up to Gibson.
もど
必ず上に戻れるよ ダミアン》
We're going to make it, Damian.
We can go a little faster.
《スピードを上げていこう｡➡
ダミアンを早くひなたに出して
体を温めないと》
I need to get Damian under the sun, to warm him up.
Forty minutes of oxygen left.
《酸素残量 あと４０分‼》
らっかちてん
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)バギーの落下地点まで
あと３０分程度だ｡
It'll be another thirty minutes before we reach the buggy crash site.
もし その場にいなかったら…
やっかい
厄介だな｡
It could get ugly if they're not there.
いるさ｡移動すれば危険が増すこと
ぐらい ２人はわかっているよ｡
They'll be there.
I'm sure they know it's dangerous to move about.
むった
ほしか
(南波六太)星加さん ﾋｭｰｽﾄﾝに
たの
頼めませんか？
Hoshika...
Can you relay a message to Houston?
(星加)何を？
What?
バディたちのビートルの
行き先を➡
Can you ask them to have Buddy, in the Beetle,
もっとこっちの方に
へんこう
変更してもらえないか｡
head toward this direction?
なんで そこに？
Why should they head there?
日々人は多分…
じっとしていないからです｡
Hibito is probably
on the move.
ナサ
(NASA職員)要は ２人が この
ゆる
緩やかな場所から➡
Here is the basis for their logic.
The slope in this area isn't as steep.
谷を登ろうとしていると
かてい
仮定して➡
In other words, JAXA assumes that the two astronauts will try to climb up here.
ビートルを こっちへ
向かわせては という➡
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡからの一案です｡
きゅうじょ
ダメだ｡救助が来るまで➡
No,
they're more likely to be waiting for help at the accident site.
落下した現場で
たいき
かのうせい
待機している可能性の方が高い｡
ビートルは そのまま
バギーの落下地点に向かわせろ｡
Have the Beetle maintain its course toward the point where the buggy fell.
よし｡
Okay.
ヒューストン ヒューストン
おうとう
応答してくれ！
Houston, Houston. Do you read me?
ヒューストン こちら ヒビト｡
ヒューストン！
Houston, this is Hibito.
Houston!
フレディ！バディ！こちらヒビト｡
カレン！リンダ！応答してくれ！
Freddy! Buddy!
This is Hibito!
Karen! Linda! Do you read me?
《クソッ…クソッ》
Damn...
Damn!
(管制官)宇宙服のアラート信号を
とらえました！➡
We've received a spacesuit alert!
ダミアンはヒビトと一緒にいます｡
通話は出来ませんが➡
Damian is with Hibito.
We're unable to communicate, but they've both made it out of the ravine.
２人とも
だっしゅつ
谷を脱出したようです！
ふぅ～っ よかった｡
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)場所は？
Whew, that's a relief...
Where are they?
バギーが落ちた地点から 谷を背に
３時の方角へ２０キロ地点です｡
Twenty kilometers, in a three o'clock direction from the crash site.
２０キロ!?
してい
ＪＡＸＡが指定してたポイントだ｡
Twenty kilometers?
That's the point JAXA indicated.
フレディ達に伝えて
すぐ向かわせろ｡
Tell Freddy and Buddy to head there immediately.
了解｡
Roger that.
(管制官)≪た…大変だ！≫
どうした？
Th-This is terrible!
What's wrong?
(管制官)ヒ…ヒビトの酸素が…➡
H-Hibito has...
あと１０分も もちません！
under ten minutes of oxygen left!
Damn it...
《クソッ こいつのスピードじゃ
ヒビト達の とこまで➡
In this thing, it'll take twenty minutes to catch Hibito!
２０分以上 かかっちまう｡
それじゃ 間に合わねえ！》
We won't make it in time!
Hibito...
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
ヒビト…｡
Wait here until help comes, Damian.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
助けが来るまで
ここにいろ ダミアン｡➡
ギブソンの影にいれば
きゅうげき
じょうしょう
急激な温度上昇も弱まるよ｡
Gibson should shade you from any sudden heat spikes.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
どこへ… 行くんだ ヒビト｡
Where are you going, Hibito?
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
前からさ…一度でいいから
やってみたかったんだよな｡
There's something I've always wanted to try.
ﾎﾞｲｽﾗｲﾀｰ
月面を…ひとりで散歩｡
Taking a walk on the moon by myself.
Eight minutes of oxygen left...
《酸素残量…８分｡➡
８分か…クソッ！》
Eight minutes, huh?
Damn!
《どうせ死ぬんなら また
あの谷に落っこちて…➡
If I have to die, I'd rather go back to the ravine
まんてん
満天の星でも
見ながらが いいな｡➡
and look up at the stars.
そうするか》
Might as well.
Th-That's...
あ…あれは？
《変更だ》
Change in plans.
ハァハァ…ハァハァ…｡
ブライ…アン…｡
Brian...
おやじ
《親父のような…
あにき
兄貴のような…➡
He was like a father, like a big brother.
だいせんぱい
あるいは 友人のような大先輩》
Like a friend who'd been through it all.
I'm here, Hibito.
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅来てやったぞ ヒビト｡➡
大先輩 ブライアン･Ｊが…➡
The veteran Brian Jay...
来てやったぞ⦆
...came to see you.
ハァ…ちゃんとある｡
It's real.
うす
げんかく
酸素が薄くなって幻覚を
見てんのかと思った｡
I thought it might be a hallucination, induced by low oxygen.
ハァ…｡
《そうか…》
I see...
《ブライアンがこれを…ここに➡
Brian put this here...
兄弟で月面に立つ事を願って…》
Because he hoped both brothers would stand on the moon together.
《悪いな…ムッちゃん…》
Sorry,
Mu...
さんそきょうきゅうていし
(管制官)酸素供給 停止！➡
Oxygen supply exhausted.
宇宙服内の空気中酸素は
かこうちゅう
２０％から下降中！
Oxygen within spacesuit falling under twenty percent!
ぐっ…ぐああ～…っ！
ハァハァ…頭が…ぐぅ！
My head!
うっ…ぐああ～っ！
ハァハァ…ハッハッ…！
Damn!
《くそ‼…死ぬのか…！》
Am I gonna die?
《体が…熱い！》
My body is burning up...
ああ…ああ…ハァハァ…｡
⦅助けてやろうか？ヒビト⦆
Want me to help you, Hibito?
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅オーッス ヒビト！⦆
Yo, Hibito!
Brian...
《ブライアン…！》
(ﾌﾞﾗｲｱﾝ)⦅来てやったぞ ヒビト｡➡
Here I am, Hibito.
この大先輩 ブライアン･Ｊが…➡
The veteran Brian Jay
来てやったぞ⦆
is here to save the day.
ブライアン
(管制官)映ったぞ！ＢＲＩＡＮの
カメラにヒビトが映った！
We have visual!
We have Hibito on Brian's camera!
(ｸﾗｳﾄﾞ)ヒビトは無事か!?
たお
わかりません｡倒れてます｡
Is Hibito okay?
I can't tell! He's on the ground!
ハァハァ…うっ…｡
He's moving!
動いた！立とうとしてるんだ！
He's trying to stand!
Hibito!
(管制官)ヒビト！
そうだ日々人！立て！
ＢＲＩＡＮから酸素を受け取れ！
Yes, Hibito!
Stand up!
Take oxygen from Brian!
(吾妻)日々人～‼
Hibito!
ハァッ！ハァ！ハァ！
ハァ！ハァ！ハァ！
ハハッ ハァ…ブライアン…｡
Brian...
やっぱり…来てくれるんだな｡
あんたは…｡
You really did come for me...
現在
あらた
《改めて思えば…➡
Looking back now,
やっぱ助かったのは
きせき
奇跡っぽいよな…》
it's a miracle that I'm alive.
(バディ)オイ！ヒビト‼
Hey, Hibito!
I have a new exercise for you.
ホレホレ 別メニューだぜ
カモン カモン！
Come on! Come on!
ハイヨ…今度は
どこに効くメニューだい？
Right...
Which body part am I working on now?
多分 ここらへんだ｡
This part, I'd say.
That was lame, Buddy...
そりゃくせぇや バディ｡
(バディ)そうかもな｡ハハハッ…｡
It was, right?
As you place your hopes on the distant moon
And leave on your journey
You smile in spite of your loneliness
Because you believe in yourself
It doesn't matter if your wings don't match
Spread them out
As you
begin your long journey (try now) (try now)
I'm sure you can make it
Please don't hesitate
to move straight forward
You took
all your pain and sorrow (no more) (no more)
And turned it into your strength
So I'm sure even your destiny to fight many a battle
Is on your side
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#54 Do I Have Good Luck?
We control our own lives.
＜人生は コントロールが利く｡
俺も みんなも➡
You, me, and everyone are all where we are in life by choice.
自分をコントロールして
ここまで来たんだよな➡
あの場所から＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Do I Have Good Luck?"
＜ヘックション！
くしゃみが止まらねえ＞
I can't stop sneezing!